so
what i want to talk next is how do we
solve the pagerank equation how do we
actually compute
the vector r the
idea here is to use the method called uh
power iteration
and what we would like to do is we'd
like to do the following right
given a graph on n nodes we want to use
an interrupt we will use an integrative
procedure
that will update over time
our rank vector r and the idea will be
that we
we start the procedure by assigning each
node some
initial random pagerank score and then
we are going to repeat our iterative
process
until this vector r stabilizes and the
way we are going to measure whether it
stabilizes will say
here is our previous estimate now t
runs over the iteration of our algorithm
where we say this is our previous
estimate
in the vector r this is our new estimate
in vector r
and if the coordinates the entries in
the vector
don't change too much they change less
than epsilon then we are done
and the equation we are going to iterate
is written here
basically node j will say my new
estimate of my importance
is simply take the estimate of the
nodes i that point to me from the
previous step
you know divide each one by the out
degree of node i sum them up and that is
my new importance
and we are just going to iterate this um
you know a couple of times and it's
uh it's guaranteed to converge to the
uh to this uh to the solution which is
essentially saying this is guaranteed to
find me
the leading eigenvector of the
underlying uh
matrix m so um
the method that does this what i
explained is called power iteration
where um basically the way we are going
to
do this to just write it again in this
very simple form
we initialize vector r you know let's
call
in calling initialization to be time
zero to be simply
you know every node has let's say the
same importance or you can assign random
importances
and then we will simply iterate you know
new estimate of
r equals m times a previous estimate of
r and we are going to iterate this
equation
uh for long enough until the the
uh and the entry wise differences
between estimating the previous round
and in the next round
when the sum of these differences uh is
less than epsilon and again
notice that this equation is exactly
this equation right this is just
written in two different ways but it's
exactly the same thing
one last thing to say is you can use the
what is called l1 norm so the sum of the
absolute differences
here you could also use let's say
euclidean norm so
some of the squares of absolute
differences uh if you like
um and generally it takes about 50
iterations you have to compute about 50
50 you have to compute this product 50
times before you
reach this stationary distribution or
this limiting
solution so basically you can compute
pagerank
by a couple of uh matrix vector
multiplies
uh and you are done and this is
important because you know google
is computing this page rank every day
over the entire web graph right of
tens of billions of uh of nodes uh
and i know hundreds of billions of edges
right so this is really really scalable
and you can you can compute it on the on
the graph that
captures the entire web so uh
to give an example again uh power
iteration method
you know written again in a different
way our matrix
m our set of flow equations uh and what
i'm going to show you here is iterations
of the algorithm
where we set node importances to be
simply uh one third
at the beginning and now we multiply
with matrix m and you know after we
multiply once
here are the new values we multiply the
second time here are the new values
and you know the third time and as we
keep multiplying the
the the value of values of vector
r then will converge to a stationary
vector so that m really equals r
really equals m times r um and the final
importances will be 6 over 15 6 over 15
and 3 over 15. so it means
y and a will have importance of 6 over
and m will have a lower importance of 3
over 15. so
um this is this is what pagerank is
going to
give us so now that we have
seen these equations and everything
seems beautiful
we need to ask a few questions so first
question is
does this converge second question is
does it converge
to where we want and the third question
is
are the results reasonable right so
basically what i said right now is
create the graph represent it as this
matrix m
run this iterative
power iteration procedure it will
converge in about 50 steps
and you will get your vector r out of it
so let's look at this uh a bit more
carefully
so it turns out that with what i
explained so far
there are two problems the first problem
is that
some pages are what is called dead ends
they have no
outlinks and it turns out that for such
web pages
the importance the votes kind of leak
out
i will tell you what i mean by that and
then there is also a second problem
called
spider traps where all outlinks are
within the same group and the spider
traps eventually absorb
all all importance so let me now give
you an example and you will see what's
happening
so um first spider traps
here in this case right we have a links
to b and then b
has a self loop so if you run this
a power iteration over an adjacency
matrix describing this graph
what will happen is that in the end a
will have
important zero and b will have
importance one and if you think of this
why is this happening is because
wherever the random walker starts uh you
know it will traverse this edge and get
into b
and then it is just going to to to be
stuck here in b
forever so really you know after some
number of time
the random walker is is in node b with
probability one
and can never go back to a so this is
called the spider trap because the
random walker gets trapped
and at the end you know this may be uh
all the importance will be kept here in
b and you can imagine this that you know
even
if you have a super huge graph here
eventually the random walker is going to
traverse over this edge
and then be stuck forever in this uh
self loop
so that's the problem of spider traps
um and then here is the problem of dead
ends the problem of dead ends is now
that node b
has no outlink and what this means that
if you would simply
create an adjacency matrix for this
graph run the power iteration
it would converge to all zeros and
intuitively why is this happening is
that as soon as the random walker gets
to node b
the random walker has nowhere to go so
it kind of falls off the cliff
and the and it gets lost right and this
way
the the dead ends kind of this
importance
doesn't yet sum to one anymore but it
leaks
out of the graph so um
this is uh these are two problems that
we are going to address
um and you know what is the solution the
solution
is this notion of uh random jumps or
teleports
so the solution for spider traps is that
we are going to change the random walk
process a bit so basically saying
at every time the random walker will not
only choose a link at random
but can also decide to teleport itself
so let me explain what this means so we
are going to have one parameter beta
that will allow random walker to do one
of the two choices
with the probability beta you know the
random walker will decide and follow a
link at random the same way as we
discussed
um so far but with probability one minus
beta
the random walker is going to jump
teleport to a random page
and the common values of beta usually
are between 0.8 to 0.9 so it means that
you know if a random walker gets stuck
in a spider trap
it will stay here for a few steps but
it's
eventually it will it will it will be
able to teleport out right because with
some
smaller probability the random walker
will say let me just randomly teleport
to a random page so it means that
out of every web page out of every node
there is a way for you to teleport
yourself
somewhere else to basically randomly
jump somewhere else
and this is um how now spider traps are
no longer the problem because
you don't get trapped you can always uh
jump out you can always
teleport you know the scottie can all
you always kind of beam you up
that's kind of the idea um how about the
dead ends
the the the way you do this is also with
teleports essentially what you say
if you come to a dead end if you come to
node m and there's nowhere for you to go
what you what you do is you simply
teleport with probability one
right so uh you know why were the dead
dead ends the problem
dead ends were the problem because m has
no out links
so our column of this uh matrix
m the column stochastic adjacency matrix
is not is the the the column
stochasticity is
uh violated because column for node m
does not sum to one
because m has no out links so what do we
do is we fix this
by basically saying when you arrive to
know them you can you can
randomly teleport wherever you want you
can jump to any node so this means in
some sense now
now m is connected to all other nodes in
the network including
itself and you know the random walker
can choose any of these links with equal
probability and this
solves the problem of dead ends it
essentially eliminates them
so why do teleports solve the problem
right why why are dead ends and spider
traps
a problem and why do teleports solve
both of them
right spider traps in some sense are not
a mathematical problem in a sense that
the eigenva the eigenvector is still
well defined the power iteration is
going to
to converge everything is fine
mathematically but the problem is that
the
pagerank score is not what we want right
we don't want to say
there is one page on the web that is
important
uh has all the importance and everyone
else is
zero important right so the solution
here is to add teleports this means the
random walker never gets
trapped in a spider trap um and it will
be able to teleport itself out in a
finite number of steps
which means that all the nodes on the
web will now have some
importance so this basically is
uh solves us this particular issue so
spider traps
are not a mathematical problem but our
problem that
pagerank value is not becomes not what
we want
and then dead ends are a problem
mathematically
because our matrix m is not column
stochastic
anymore and our initial assumptions are
not met
so power iteration as a method does not
does not uh does not work and does not
converge
so the solution here is to make the
column the
matrix column stochastic by always
teleporting
when there is nowhere to go right
whenever you come to a node without any
outlinks you always randomly teleport
um and this is now means that basically
the same solution of teleports
both give gives us pagerank the way we
wanted to define it
intuitively and also fixes the
underlying mathematical problems
that all these concepts that i discussed
are well defined
so what is the final solution or the
google solution to this problem
um the solution is that at each step the
random walker
has two options you know it flips a coin
and with
some probability beta it's going to
follow an outlet
outlink at random and with the remaining
probability
it's going to jump to a random page so
the way now our pagerank equation
that was defined by um sergey and brin
um or page and brin back uh in uh
1998 uh is the following we say the
importance of node
j equals the beta times the importances
of node i
that point to it right divided by the
route degrees plus
1 minus beta 1 over n so the way you can
think of this is to say
if a random if how likely is a random
walker to be at node j right now
it with probability beta it decided to
follow an
uh an outlink and this means it was at
no dive it was
with some probability r sub i and it
decided to follow an
outlink towards uh node j following
you know picking the right outlink out
of the d sub i outlink has the
probability
one over d sub i so that's what's
happening here
and then we say oh and also the random
walker could come to the
node j by basically teleporting
one minus beta is probability of
teleporting now how likely is the random
walker to land
at node j node j is just one out of n
nodes so the probability that it landed
at specific node
j is one over n and this is essentially
the pagerank equation and the iteration
one can run uh just note that this
formulation here assumes
m has no dead ends the way you can do is
you can pre-process
a matrix m to remove all the dead ends
um and
or or exclusively follow random
teleports with probability one
out of dead ends so that's how you can
fix this but you can see again this is
very fast and very simple
to iterate so i just gave you the
equation
in this the flow based formulation in
some sense
you can also write it in a matrix form
where you say
my new matrix g right so
this should be g equals beta times the
stochastic matrix
m plus one minus beta
uh times the uh the matrix that has
all the entries uh one over n so this is
the random teleportation
matrix and this is the the transition
matrix over the edges of the graph
um and then you have this again
recursive equation that r
equals g times r and you can iterate
this
power power iteration will still work um
and if you ask
what should be the beta value that i
that i set
in practice we take beta to be between
0.8
uh and 0.9 which means that you the
random walker takes about
five steps on the average before it
decides to jump
just to be very clear the random walk is
just the intuition and we'd never
simulate the random walk right in the
previous lecture we actually said let's
simulate the random walk here
we don't simulate the random walk but in
some sense we think of it as being
run infinitely long and then we say
we show that actually we can compute
this infinitely long random walk by
basically solving this recursive
equation
by basically computing the the leading
eigenvector
of this uh graph transformed matrix
uh that i call g uh here so
the random walk is just an intuition
because we never
truly um we never truly
uh simulated so to show you how this
works here is my
little graph on three nodes uh here's
the
matrix m uh notice that uh the node
n is a is a spider trap so what do i do
now is i
add also this um random teleport
links so i have this matrix
1 over n let's say that my beta is 0.8
so now my new stochastic
transition matrix g is written here
right it's
0.8 times the matrix of link transitions
plus
point to the matrix of random jumps
where basically you can think of this
that every column says
if no if a random server is at a given
node
then this is the probability
distribution where the random surfer
is going to jump and if you add these
two together you get a new
transition matrix now that includes both
traversing over the links of the graph
as well as randomly jumping
here is how you can think of this in
terms of transition probabilities these
are now
in some sense transition probabilities
of a random walker random surfer
and then you can multiply r with g
multiple times here is the
r0 and now we are multiplying it over
and over and over again
and you know after some number of
iterations it's going to converge
and it converges to 7 over 33 5 over 33
and 21 over 33 so it means that
node m in this graph will be the most
important followed by y
followed by a right and the reason why m
is so important is because
it's kind of a spider trap but we also
are able to teleport out
now if intuitively this is uh you know
no damn
kind of collects too much importance you
can increase uh value of beta
and the importance of node m is going to
decrease
and just to show you an idea how this
how this looks like
in in a bit more interesting graph this
is a graph where node size corresponds
to its pagerank weight and also there is
a number
that tells you what the pagerank score
of the node and what do you notice for
example why is pagerank so cool
it's cool because for example first
notice all nodes have non-zero
importance so even these nodes here
that have no in-links they still have
some importance because the random
jumper can always jump to them another
thing notice is that for example node b
has a lot of in-links and so that's why
it has high importance
right notice that for example node e has
you know it has five
in links six in links and uh node b also
has
six in links but because node e gets
most of the in links from these
unimportant pages
its importance is you know eight versus
b who is 38.
so b is much more important because it
gets
in links from these other nodes that
have higher importance than these
little blue nodes another thing to
notice is for example node c
has only one in-link but because it gets
it from this
super important node b its importance is
also very very high
right you see for example also that uh
here node e has
uh some uh uh you know some importance
uh d has less f has less uh they both
have the same importance
d and f because they both get one in
link from node
so notice how these uh importances are
very nuanced
and they take a lot of different
considerations into account
that all make sense in a sense of i want
a lot of in-links
i want in-links from important nodes
even if i have one in-link but somebody
very important links to me
that means i'm very important um and so
and
so on and so forth so this is why
this notion of pagerank is so so useful
and also there is a lot of mathematical
beauty
um behind its uh its definition and we
can efficiently compute it
for very large scale graphs
so to summarize we talked about how do
we solve the pagerank
uh scores we solve them by iterating
this
equation r equals g times r
and this can be efficiently computed
using power iteration of the stochastic
matrix g
um and adding uniform teleportation
solves both the issues with dead ends as
well as the issue with spider traps